<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Meta-models on Stefano Coretta</title>
    <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/categories/meta-models/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Meta-models on Stefano Coretta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://stefanocoretta.github.io/categories/meta-models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My researcher&#39;s positionality statement</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/positionality/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/positionality/</guid>
      <description>1 Overview This is my researcher’s positionality statement (for context, see Darwin Holmes 2020; Jafar 2018).
 The term positionality both describes an individual’s world view and the position they adopt about a research task and its social and political context. The individual’s world view or ‘where the researcher is coming from’ concerns ontological assumptions (an individual’s beliefs about the nature of social reality and what is knowable about the world), epistemological assumptions (an individual’s beliefs about the nature of knowledge) and assumptions about human nature and agency (individual’s assumptions about the way we interact with our environment and relate to it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods as theory</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/methods-as-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/methods-as-theory/</guid>
      <description>At least in linguistics, there is a general tendency to contrast theory with methods. This dichotomy is also reflected in the classification of academic papers as theoretical or methodological.
In this brief post I will argue that the theory/methods divide is epistemologically incoherent, and I will instead propose a taxonomy in which methods are subsumed under theory and are part of it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
