<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>phonology on Stefano Coretta</title>
    <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/tags/phonology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in phonology on Stefano Coretta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017-2019 Stefano Coretta</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://stefanocoretta.github.io/tags/phonology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On the phonotactic restrictions of Proto-Indoeuropean roots</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/on-the-phonotactic-restrictions-of-proto-indoeuropean-roots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/on-the-phonotactic-restrictions-of-proto-indoeuropean-roots/</guid>
      <description>Proto-Indoeuropean lexicon is based on monosyllabic roots which have an alternating (ablaut) root vowel preceded and followed by consonants. In this post, I will share some thoughts on the phonotactic restrictions which seem to dictate which consonants can cooccur in a root. I will focus here on stops and laryngeal features. Although I have some formal training in Indoeuropean linguistics, what follows is more of an academic game, so I invite the reader not to expect a fully developed argument.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting tongue contours with ggplot2</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/plotting-tongue-contours-with-ggplot2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/plotting-tongue-contours-with-ggplot2/</guid>
      <description>When plotting tongue contours data obtained from ultrasound tongue imaging in R using ggplot2, a common option to smooth over the individual contours and show the general pattern is to use geom_smooth(methood = &#34;loess&#34;). However, as I will show in this post, in certain cases this method leads to very disorted contours. Such distortion is more or less always present, although at a lower degree in less extreme cases.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vowel formants trajectories and tidy data</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/vowel-formants-trajectories-and-tidy-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/vowel-formants-trajectories-and-tidy-data/</guid>
      <description>With the advent of more powerful statistical methods for accessing time series data, it is now more common to compare whole vowel formant trajectories rather then just using average formant values.
Sometimes, the output of the Praat script used for extracting formats data gives us a ‘wide format’ dataset. In this format, separate columns contain formant values for each interval within the vowel. Normally, values are extracted every 10% or 5% intervals within the vowel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short review of phonological databases</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/2014-06-30-short-review-phonological-databases/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/2014-06-30-short-review-phonological-databases/</guid>
      <description>A review of available phonological databases (2014).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>