<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>concepts on Stefano Coretta</title>
    <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/tags/concepts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in concepts on Stefano Coretta</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://stefanocoretta.github.io/tags/concepts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On phonologisation</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/2021-04-24-on-phonologisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/2021-04-24-on-phonologisation/</guid>
      <description>After the post on the definition of random effects, I thought about writing another one on the definition of phonologisation.
As part of my PhD thesis on the effect of consonant voicing on vowel duration, I briefly reviewed the five definitions of phonologisation I could find in the literature. This post includes text from my thesis and expands on a few points.
The main take-away of the sections to follow is that what one means with phonologisation is (unsurprisingly) dependent on the set of assumptions that are part of the framework within which the term is used.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods as theory</title>
      <link>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/methods-as-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://stefanocoretta.github.io/post/methods-as-theory/</guid>
      <description>At least in linguistics, there is a general tendency to contrast theory with methods. This dichotomy is also reflected in the classification of academic papers as theoretical or methodological.
In this brief post I will argue that the theory/methods divide is epistemologically incoherent, and I will instead propose a taxonomy in which methods are subsumed under theory and are part of it.
1 What is theory? The term theory is used with different senses in different domains.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
